June 22, 1941. With 134 divisions in full combat capacity and 73 more divisions to
deploy behind the front, Nazi Germany, under the code name Operation Barbarossa,
invades the Soviet Union, its ally in the war against Poland. Hitler
He sees the invasion as part of his plan to provide the German nation with "Lebensraum",
which means "living space" and an opportunity to destroy communism, an ideology he detests.
In the first six weeks after the German attack, the Soviet Union
suffered catastrophic military losses and during the war the German armies
eventually capturing some 5.7 million Soviet Red Army troops.
Among them is a man who will participate in the uprising in the
Sobibor extermination center during which he will brutally kill two of the
11 members of the camp's SS personnel. This soldier's name is Simjon Rosenfeld.
Simjon Moiseyevich Rosenfeld, son of a tailor, was born on October 1, 1922 in the
Ukrainian village of Ternivka. Simjon had two sisters and, as a child, he experienced famine.
artificial explosion known as the Holodomor, which devastated Soviet Ukraine in early
the 1930s and took the lives of millions of Ukrainians. Young Simjon grew up in his village
native and attended a Jewish school, which in 1936 was converted into a Ukrainian school.
World War II began on September 1, 1939 when Nazi Germany invaded
Poland. Great Britain and France maintained their guarantee of protection of Poland's border and
declared war on Germany two days later. However, Poland found itself fighting a
war on two fronts when the Soviet Union invaded the country from the east on September 17.
The Polish government fled the country that same day and after intense bombing, Warsaw was
officially surrendered to the Germans on September 28, 1939. In accordance with the protocol
In secret of their non-aggression pact, Germany and the Soviet Union divided Poland on 29
September and the last stand of the Polish units ended on October 6.
In 1940, Simjon graduated from high school and, at the age of 18,
He was drafted into the Red Army, where he served in the 150th Heavy Artillery Regiment.
On June 22, 1941, less than two years after the start of World War II,
Nazi Germany, under the code name Operation Barbarossa,
invaded the Soviet Union, its ally in the war against Poland.
In June of that same year, Rosenfeld's regiment was among the cities
from Minsk and Baranovichy, then part of the Soviet Socialist Republic
Belarus. Rosenfeld was wounded during heavy fighting and captured by the Germans,
becoming a prisoner of war.
The SS imprisoned him in the Minsk ghetto, where, for two years,
He had to do hard physical labor. The Germans had established the ghetto
of Minsk in the northwestern part of Minsk at the end of July 1941 and about 80,000 people were crammed there
people, including Jews from nearby towns. Between November 1941 and October 1942,
The German government deported nearly 24,000 Jews from Germany to Minsk,
Austria and the Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia. SS and police authorities fired shots.
or gassed (in special gas vans) most of them upon arrival at Maly Trostinets,
a small town almost 13 kilometers east. The occupation authorities
The Germans housed the others in a separate section of the Minsk ghetto, segregated from
local Belarusian Jews. Little contact was allowed between the residents of the two ghettos.
The Germans destroyed the Minsk ghetto in the autumn of 1943. While the SS killed
about 4,000 Jews remaining in Maly Trostinets, there were some Jews, including Simjon Rosenfeld,
who were taken by train to Lublin, in German-occupied Poland,
in what would become the Majdanek concentration camp. However, after waiting a
One day at the gates of the camp, they were told that there was no room and that they would be taken to Sobibor.
When a Polish railway worker told them they were going to be gassed and incinerated there,
Nobody believed him. The occupants of the Rosenfeld car had even opened
a hole in the bottom of the car to use as a bathroom,
and they could have escaped for him, but no one did because they couldn't believe they were going to
kill everyone. By the time they reached the camp called Sobibor, it was too late.
German police and SS authorities built Sobibor in the spring of 1942.
It was the second of three killing centers established as part of Operation Reinhard,
the code name for the German plan to murder the Jews of the General Government. It was
implemented by the leader of the SS and police in Lublin, SS General Odilo Globocnik.
At its largest, the camp covered a rectangular area of 400 by 600 meters.
Branches woven into the barbed wire fence and trees planted around the perimeter
They camouflaged the site and a minefield more than 15 meters wide surrounded the camp.
The deportations to Sobibor took place between May 1942,
when regular gassing operations began, and the fall of 1943. Most of the
Jews taken to Sobibor were immediately gassed with carbon monoxide that had been
Introduced into the gas chambers from a motor. Around 250,000 victims
were murdered in this extermination center. Camp officials
They chose a small handful of prisoners who seemed fit or capable, to supplement
the offer of forced labor at Sobibor. Simjon was put to work hauling bricks.
When the Rosenfeld transport arrived at Sobibor in September 1943, they took out
everyone from the train. Rosenfeld later recalled that the Germans had separated the soldiers
Jews of the Jews, but the SS were afraid to shoot them because they were still considered
prisoners of war. In total, 80 Jews from Minsk were held at Sobibor. Later,
when one of the prisoners asked a German camp guard where they were
the rest of his friends on the train, he pointed to the smoking chimney and replied that they were: “over there.”
As early as early 1943, Jewish prisoners at Sobibor began to fear for their lives.
lives because the murderous operations at Sobibor were coming to an end.
The inmates of Sobibor knew what awaited them, as the prisoners of Belzec,
who did the same work as them, had sewn messages into their clothes before
of being killed by Sobibor guards who shot them the same day they arrived
to the camp. The next day, the prisoners there found all their clothes full of
blood. Jaim Engel, a Polish Jewish prisoner, found a note in a pocket that read:
“We worked at Belzec for a year and didn't know where we would be sent to.”
continuation. They said it would be Germany. Now we are in Sobibor and we know what
wait. Keep in mind that they will kill you too! Avenge us!” And so they did!
In response, the prisoners organized a resistance group in late spring.
of 1943. This group increased in number and military training skills with
The arrival of Jewish prisoners of war from the Red Army ghetto
from Minsk. The prisoners finally had the necessary experience to escape.
When Alexander Pechersky, leader of the planned uprising,
asked Simjon Rosenfeld if he was capable of killing a man with an axe, Rosenfeld,
who was 21 at the time, replied: "I am not capable of killing a human being,
but I can kill a Nazi." The targets were carefully
selected and the first person killed by the prisoners was the deputy commandant of Sobibor,
Johann Niemann, who was the highest-ranking SS officer on duty that day.
With approximately 600 prisoners in the camp, who knew
The plan started the revolt on October 14, 1943 at 4 p.m.
Niemann was killed by Soviet prisoner of war Alexander Shubayev,
who buried the axe in the back of his head and split his skull. He died instantly.
At 16:15, Oberscharführer Siegfried Graetschus, the German in charge of the guard
Ukrainian from Trawniki, arrived at the shoe store to pick up an order. While a prisoner held
firmly grasping the Nazi's leg, pretending to take off his boots, Simjon Rosenfeld and his
fellow prisoner Arkady Wajspapir came out of the back room and smashed the Nazi's skull with
the axe. Then his deputy, the Ukrainian guard Rai Klatt, came in and called his boss by
phone. He was also attacked and killed. An hour after the attack began
uprising, the rebels killed a total of 11 SS officers.
Then chaos reigned in the place. The prisoners had to escape.
climbing a barbed wire fence or running out the front door to
through a minefield under intense machine gun fire.
Some stepped on mines. Others gave up and didn't run.
Not a meter more. Simjon Rosenfeld was one of those who ran. He later recalled:
"I wasn't afraid because I didn't have time to think about fear. I only thought about getting out alive."
About 300 prisoners managed to escape from the extermination center. Approximately 100 people
were caught in the raid that followed the uprising. However, about 50 inmates
escaped from Sobibor and survived the war. After the uprising, on the orders of Heinrich
Himmler, the SS-trained guards and Trawniki shot the remaining prisoners,
They razed the extermination side of the camp and buried all the evidence.
and planted trees to disguise the area. Among those who were not captured were also
Simjon Rosenfeld was there. With a small group of people that included former prisoners
from Sobibor and Jews who had escaped from German murder operations, went into hiding in
the forest for eleven months. At the end of July 1944, nine months after the uprising,
The Red Army liberated the city of Chelm, located about 50 km from Sobibor. The soldiers
Soviets found Rosenfeld 2 months later in a nearby area and soon after asked
to the Soviet command to send him to the front. However, the Soviets doubted that he really
would have survived two years of captivity. After careful evaluation by
From the Soviet counterintelligence unit SMERSH, Simjon Rosenfeld was sent to fight
in the 1st Belorussian Front. He participated in the crossing of the Vistula River and during the battle for the city
from Poznan in the winter of 1944-1945, Simjon was seriously wounded. He was almost killed
had a limb amputated when a young Jewish doctor advised him to refuse the operation.
After being discharged from the hospital, Rosenfeld was deemed unfit for
combat and was sent to Berlin as commander of a unit guarding
the army's food supplies. There he would witness the end of the war.
On a column of the Reichstag, the German parliament, he scribbled the following inscription:
"Baranovichi-Sobibor-Berlin". In 1945, Rosenfeld received medals for his
combat services and for his courage and returned to Ukraine, to his birthplace, Ternivka.
There he discovered that the Germans had shot his entire family at the end of May 1942. When
He learned that his uncle in the nearby town was still alive, so he went there. On January 15,
In 1946, Simjon married his uncle's daughter, Yevgeniya. They settled in the town.
Ukrainian Gaivoron, where Simjon worked as a photography workshop director.
They raised two children and followed their children to Odessa in 1975. Although the Sobibor uprising
was not prominent enough in the Soviet Union, in 1963, after 20 years,
Simjon met Aleksandr Pecherskii and other survivors of the uprising. They continued
reuniting until 1990, when Pecherskii died and the Rosenfelds emigrated to Israel.
Although the Nazis buried all the evidence from the Sobibor camp and planted a forest there,
Archaeological work that began in 2007 revealed the
exact location of the gas chambers in 2014. When Rosenfeld was informed of this, he said:
"I can't believe they found it, the Nazis destroyed everything."
the countryside. It's hard to imagine anything left there now." Over the years,
Archaeologists have unearthed thousands of personal objects: rings,
lockets, earrings, jewelry, perfume bottles, medicine bottles and utensils.
When Simjon Rosenfeld died on June 3, 2019, in a nursing home in Rechovot
near Tel Aviv, Israel, he was 96. He was the last known survivor of Sobibor.
Many tears were shed for Simjon Rosenfeld.
Thanks for watching World History Channel, don't forget to like and subscribe.
and click on the notification bell so you don't miss out
our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel